Vast open plains
Immense spaces
Eerie silence
But any feeling
of emptiness is an illusion
The plains of our planet support the greatest gatherings of wildlife on earth
At the heart of
all that happens here
is a single
living thing
grass
This miraculous plant
covers a quarter
of all the lands of the earth
Grasslands exist
wherever there
is a little rain
but not enough to
sustain a forest
Some are huge
The Central
Asian steppe alone
extends one third
of the way around our planet
It's summer
and eagles
effortlessly cruise the thermals
scanning the
ground beneath for signs of prey
In the distant
reaches of Outer Mongolia
one of the planet'
s great migrations is underway
Few people ever
see this extraordinary annual event
Mongolian gazelle
Two million are
thought to live here
But no one
really knows
For much
of the time
they're scattered
through this vast landscape
But once a year
they come together
to have
their young
Nearly all will
give birth within the next ten days
Out in the open
communal carving
is the safest way to have young
With so many
pairs of eyes keeping watch
It's almost impossible for predators to sneak up
There are
no bushes
no trees
There's only one
thing to hide behind
Grass
And it's not
very effective
Predators also have a hard time raising their young on open grassland
Without trees
eagles have to
nest directly on the ground
All inhabitants
of the great plains
are exposed
to the elements
Fire sparks
panic in the herd
Gazelles are
born to run
And even young
calves easily outpace the flames
If they can
avoid being trampled
With nothing to
stand in its way
The blaze consumes anything that can't flee
Huge quantities of grass
valuable food
have been lost
And with it
the old
and the weak
The gazelles move
on to new pastures
And leave the
desolation behind them
From the ashes
rises the phoenix
grass
the incredible survivor
Because it grows
from a protected part at the base of its stems
grass is almost
indestructible
Able to repair
and reproduce itself rapidly
It covers more of
the Earth's land than any other plant
And feeds more
wildlife than any other
Red billed quillia
One and a half
billion swarm across the savannahs of Africa
These are the
most numerous birds on earth
Some flocks
are so vast
that they can
take five hours to pass overhead
Only grass can
feed plagues of these proportions
The ravenous
hordes devour the seeds
And the leaves and stems are cropped by great herds of antelope
The East African savannahs alone sustain nearly two million wildebeest
They trim the
grass down to its roots
leaving little
in their wake
But within days
the plant will recover
and continue to
sustain the biggest herds on earth
Grass is not
confined to the tropics
It manages to grow even in the bitter conditions of the Arctic
Beyond the limits
of the last tree
The planet is
barren and ice locked
A frozen no man's
land at the end of the Earth
But for a short
time each year
The long dark
winter releases its grip
Temperatures rise
and grass that has lain dormant and frozen throughout the winter
sprouts once more
Green returns
to the Arctic
The receding ice
reveals an immense flat plain
the size
of Australia
This is the
Arctic tundra
It's a desolate
silent wilderness
but it's
about to change
Snow geese
They winter along
the Gulf of Mexico
And in spring
they fly the
entire length of North America
To reach the
Arctic tundra
Five million
birds make this journey every year
Their marathon
migration is almost 3，000 miles long
and has taken
them three months
Exhausted
and starving
they touch down
inside the Arctic Circle
Back at their
traditional breeding grounds
at last
Snow geese
pair for life
As soon as
couples arrive
they must stake a
claim to a nesting patch
Ideal sites are
in short supply
And quarrelsome
neighbours are all around
Disputes
can be vicious
Point taken
It's a long
way to travel
But for a
short period
the tundra is the
ideal place for a grazer
The grass grows
vigorously during the short intense summer
And there are
fewer predators than further south
Here
geese can nest on
the ground in relative safety
Nonetheless
this female must
incubate her eggs for three weeks
And throughout this time
she will be
very vulnerable
An Arctic fox
surveys the colony
She's been
waiting for the geese all winter
Sneaking up
unnoticed is impossible
Perhaps fortune
will favour the bold
The colony is
well defended
There are no
easy pickings here
She's driven
away from every nest
But hunger
compels her to continue
There are more
eggs here than she can possibly eat now
But the nesting
season is short
So she stashes
much of her plunder for later in the year
When all the
geese have gone
Further south
other
bigger predators
prowle the tundra
Wolves
for them finding
food on the plains is an even greater challenge
Not only is
their prey seasonal
it's also
hard to find
They've been
searching for days without a sign
Somewhere in this
immense landscape
there is
food for them
This is it
caribou
Travelling
30 miles a day
They can cover
nearly 2000 miles during the summer months
The wolves will
starve if they don't find the caribou
But it's no easy
task to locate prey
That never
stops travelling
Biting flies and
the quest for new pasture
drives the
migration ever onwards
The wolf has
finally picked up the trail
The caribou are close
At last，a chance
The hunt is on
The wolf
panics the herd
and the weak and
young are singled out
A calf is
separated from its mother
At the
goose colony
it's high summer
and eggs
are hatching
The young all
emerge within a day or two
A marvel of timing
The colony is now
home to a million goslings
The fox is still
gathering all she can get
Sometimes
one mouth
simply isn't enough
One will
have to do
Not all
food is stored
Some is
needed right now
She has seven
hungry cubs to feed
As their
appetites grow
the mother must
work tirelessly to raise her family
Only fat
healthy cubs will
survive the Arctic winter
The vast majority
of the Goslings are still flourishing
Their parents
lead them down to the safety of the water
As soon as they'
re strong enough to make the journey
For the foxes
boom time has
come to an end
But the mother has given her cubs the best possible start in life
The geese will
continue grazing the tundra
until the
summer ends
and they're
forced to head south for the winter
At these latitudes
the sun's
rays are weak
and grass can
only grow here for a few months a year
But further south
summers are longer
and the
grasslands flourish
The prairies
of North America
This rich pasture
once supported
the greatest herds ever seen on our planet
There were once
60 million bison
But no animal is
immune to intensive hunting by man
Or the destruction of its habitat
And a century ago
the bison were
reduced to barely a thousand
Now
thanks to
rigorous protection
the species
is recovering
The growing
season is long
and the grass
here can support herds all year round
Male bison
weigh in at one ton
In high summer
the bulls are fat
from the rich grazing
and in
prime condition
But only a
few will mate
Exactly which few
is about to
be decided
On temperate
plains around the world
Summer is a time
for growth and reproduction
Now the grass
produces its flowers
New colours also
come to the plains
The northern flowering is mirrored by the grasslands of the southern hemisphere
And nowhere is more impressive than on the veldt of South Africa
Not all
temperate plains
are so rich and
colourful in the summer
This is midsummer
on the Tibetan plateau
the highest great
plain in the world
Despite the
conditions
grass survives
and in sufficient quantities
to support the
highest of all grazing herds
those of
the wild yak
Even in summer
life is hard
Temperatures
rarely rise above freezing
and the
air is thin
It's also
exceptionally dry
for one
very big reason
The Himalayas
The great mountain range acts as a barrier
Preventing clouds
moving in from the south
And this casts a
giant rain shadow
That leaves
Tibet high and dry
Grass
clings to life
even as
desiccating winds
remove what
little moisture remains in the soil
So long as
grass can survive
so can grazers
Wild ass
The males are
fighting to win territories
Those that
hold the best
are more likely
to attract a herd of females
It's a
frisky business
That counts
as a victory
But he can't assume the females will actually turn up
Female asses are
mysterious creatures
They come and
go as they please
And much of their
behaviour seems unfathomable
To an outsider
They're the great
nomads of the plateau
And will often trek vast distances across these parched plains
In search of oases
But when they
do find paradise
They are liable
to feed and drink for just a few hours
And then head
back to the dust
For no
apparent reason
Wild ass are the
most conspicuous pioneers of this high frontier
But the most numerous grazer in Tibet lives underground
Pika
a relative
of the rabbit
it too
feeds on grass
On the
exposed plateau
pykhas never
stray far from their burrows
But even so
squatters
will move in
given
half a chance
While groundpeckers and snowfinches can be a nuisance
they're
worth tolerating
because they provide a valuable early warning system
The bizarre
Tibetan fox
The piker'
s nemesis
When stalking
it keeps
below the skyline
perhaps helped by
its curious body shape
But why the
square head？
In summer
the Tibetan
plateau heats up
drawing in warm
wet air from the south
But the water
never arrives
As the moist
air approaches
it's forced
upwards by the Himalayas
And condenses
into huge rain clouds
These clouds drop
all their water on the southern side of the mountains
The very peaks
that keep Tibet dry
are responsible
for the monsoon rains falling farther south
and the
greening of India
Here
soaked by rain
and bathed in tropical sun
grass reaches
its full potential
Elephant grass is
the tallest in the world
Grass that towers
over an elephant
can conceal all
sorts of surprises
The male
lesser florican
It's hard work
getting noticed
when you go
courting in high grass
The long grass
plains of tropical India
are home to some
of the largest grass eating mammals on our planet
And some of
the smallest
Pygmy hogs are no
bigger than rabbits
They're the
tiniest and rarest of all wild pigs
The female is
busy collecting grass
but not for eating
She's
building a nest
Each piglet may
be small enough
to fit in the
palm of a hand
But she
does have ten
This is how
grass can grow
given unlimited
sunshine and water
But on most
tropical plains across our planet
the wet season is
followed by a dry one
On the
African savannahs
grazers are marching in search of grass and water
Without rain
these plains can
become dust bowls
Grass can now
lose its hold
Elephants are in
immediate danger
They must
drink almost daily
Driven on
by thirst
They march hundreds of miles across the parched plains
Relying on memory
the matriarchs
lead their families
to those
special water holes
that saved them
in previous years
This one
still has water
But they must
share what remains
with desperately
thirsty animals
of all kinds
These are
tense times
The elephants
dominate the waterhole
But as night falls
the balance of
power will shift
Thirsty herds
continue to arrive
throughout the night
It's a cooler
time to travel
In the darkness
the tables turn
The elephant's
night vision is little better than our own
But lions have
much more sensitive eyes
The cats
are hungry
and the elephants
seem to sense it
Lions don't
usually hunt elephants
But desperate
times require desperate measures
This herd
contains calves
easier targets
But how to
reach them？
The adults
encircle their young
It's an impenetrable wall of grey
A few exhausted
stragglers are still arriving
One of
them is alone
But it's too big
for the lions to tackle
This one looks
a little smaller
A solitary lion
stands no chance
But the whole
pride is here
There are
30 of them
and they're
specialist elephant hunters
This elephant
will feed the whole pride
for at
least a week
Elephants know
these drinking holes are dangerous
But they
have no choice
The dramas
that play out here
are a
savage reminder
of how
important water is
for all life
on these plains
As the dry season
finally draws to a close
Africa's baked
savannahs undergo a radical change
Rain sweeps
across the continent
And grass
the great survivor
Rises again
And the
herds return
For months
they've been
scattered over huge areas
Clinging to
existence around tiny waterholes
Now
the good
times are back
A few African
savannas are very special
Here
rainwater
from far and wide
flows across
the flat plains
Grass is submerged
but still it grows
Flooded， burnt
baked， and frozen
grass can
withstand it all
After six
months of drought
grass replaces
dust over great areas
Fresh new shoots
draw animals from great distances
Many undertake
epic migrations to catch the boom time
Some resourceful
animals live here all the year round
Baboons are
permanent residents
But they have to
change their behaviour
If they're to
gather what they need
On the newly
flooded plains
There's
plenty to eat
But getting to it
can be a little uncomfortable
New water poses
problems for the youngsters
But they know
where to find a dry seat
A juicy snail is
ample recompense for sodden paws
Having survived
the dry barren times
Animals can now
reap the rewards
On this
seasonal planet
the great plains
are lands of feast and famine
At their peak
they support the
greatest gatherings of wildlife
found
anywhere on Earth